<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Testing | Behavioral Data Science</title><link>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/theme2_content/</link><atom:link href="https://www.behavioral-ds.science/theme2_content/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Testing</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>2022</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/img/logo.png</url><title>Testing</title><link>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/theme2_content/</link></image><item><title>Slipping to the Extreme: A Mixed-Method to Explain How Extreme Opinions Infiltrate Online Discussions</title><link>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/theme2_content/icwsm2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/theme2_content/icwsm2022/</guid><description>&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/HwFq3ywanp4" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;p>In our &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2109.00302.pdf">recent paper&lt;/a> accepted at &lt;a href="https://www.icwsm.org/2022/index.html/">ICWSM 2022&lt;/a>, we propose a complete solution to accelerate the qualitative analysis of problematic online speech — with a specific focus on opinions emerging from online communities — by leveraging machine learning algorithms.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Paper citation:&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>Quyu Kong, Emily Booth, Francesco Bailo, Amelia Johns, and Marian-Andrei
Rizoiu. Slipping to the Extreme: A Mixed-Method to Explain How Extreme
Opinions Infiltrate Online Discussions. In: Proceedings of the 16TH AAAI
International Conference on Web and Social Media, 2022.
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>(see full paper here: &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2109.00302.pdf">https://arxiv.org/pdf/2109.00302.pdf&lt;/a>)&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="problematic-speech-a-modern-plague">Problematic Speech: A Modern Plague&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Problematic speech is online interactions, speech, and artifacts that are inaccurate, misleading, inappropriately attributed, or altogether fabricated [1].
In 2020, the COVID-19 pandemic alerted the world to complex issues that arise from social media platforms circulating user-generated misinformation, hate speech, and conspiracy theories [2].
There are several primary types of quantitative methods for addressing problematic information, including large-scale monitoring of social media datasets [3], understanding platforms, users, and networks contributing to the &amp;ldquo;infodemic&amp;rdquo; [4], and predicting future pathways of information spreading [5].
These studies provide valuable insights into understanding how problematic information spreads and detecting which sources are reshared frequently and by which accounts.
However, these approaches often have less to say about why certain opinions and views gain traction with vulnerable groups and online communities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Qualitative research methods are well placed to address this gap.
They provide rich, contextual insights into online communities&amp;rsquo; social beliefs, values, and practices, which shape how information is shared and how opinions are formed [6].
Nevertheless, a common criticism of qualitative research is that the in-depth knowledge comes at the expense of generating insights of limited representativeness and weak robustness of the findings.
Therefore, there is a gap between the depth of insight gained from ethnographic and qualitative approaches and the breadth of knowledge gained from computational methods from data science.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our work fills this gap by proposing a mixed-method approach that combines qualitative insights, large-scale data collection, and human-in-the-loop machine learning approaches.
We apply our method to map in-depth and in-breadth the problematic information around four topics:
&lt;em>2019-20 Australian bushfire season&lt;/em>,
&lt;em>Climate change&lt;/em>,
&lt;em>COVID-19&lt;/em>, and
&lt;em>Vaccination&lt;/em>
on three social media platforms (Facebook, Twitter, and YouTube).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="our-solution-mixing-digital-ethnography-with-advanced-machine-learning">Our Solution: Mixing Digital Ethnography with Advanced Machine Learning&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="fig1.png" alt="The pipeline of machine learning accelerated qualitative research where the human-in-the-loop machine learning algorithms are employed for dataset augmentation.">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We present a complete solution that bridges and facilitates qualitative and quantitative analysis to study problematic online speech.
The pipeline consists of three components which are detailed in this section.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="deep-qualitative-study">Deep qualitative study&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The first component is the qualitative study.
We build a platform based on an open-source tool, &lt;a href="https://wikiba.se/">&lt;em>Wikibase&lt;/em>&lt;/a>, where we conduct qualitative and quantitative analysis.
Through the quantitative study, we build an ontology of problematic online speech.
We label a large number of social media postings using their topics.
Simultaneously, we construct a vocabulary of 71 opinions that we also use to label postings.
Some example opinions include:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Climate change crisis isn't real&lt;/li>
&lt;li>United Nations is corrupt&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Climate change is a UN hoax&lt;/li>
&lt;li>United Nations wants to be the global ruling government&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Vaccines cause Autism&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The World Health Organisation is corrupt&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>These opinions contain mistrust in the government and supra-national structures (e.g., UN, WHO) and typical misinformation about vaccines.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="unlabeled-data-collection">Unlabeled data collection&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Qualitative approaches analyze emerging content and construct the vocabulary simultaneously when labeling the data.
However, they lack representativeness as they tend to be overly concentrated on narrow areas of the narrative landscape.
For this reason, the second step in our methodology involves collecting data at scale.
We collect large-scale raw data using the uncovered vocabulary from the deep qualitative study.
We construct keywords (shown in the table) for each topic to crawl social media data from three platforms.
We obtain a total of &lt;strong>13,321,813&lt;/strong> postings — &lt;strong>11,437,009&lt;/strong> Facebook postings, &lt;strong>1,793,927&lt;/strong> tweets and &lt;strong>90,877&lt;/strong> YouTube comments.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="table.png" alt="keywords">&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="dataset-augmentation">Dataset augmentation&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The next step is to annotate all the postings in our dataset automatically.
We employ machine learning algorithms to augment the data labeling process with a human-in-the-loop setting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>By adopting the state-of-the-art text classification algorithm, RoBERTa [7,8], we first train the classifiers to identify problematic speech on postings annotated by the qualitative researchers.
Next, we deploy three strategies to select unlabeled data.
The active learning [9] strategy selects the data for which the classifiers are most uncertain.
The top-confidence strategy selects data that classifiers are most certain about.
The third strategy — the random strategy — randomly samples from unlabeled data.
The qualitative researchers then label the sampled data, introduce the newly labeled data in the ontology, and repeat the procedure iteratively until the predictive performance converges.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="humanintheloop-performance">Human-in-the-loop Performance&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We discuss here the convergence of prediction performance over labeling iterations.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The following plot depicts the prediction performance on the test set macro-averaged over topics (accuracy in the left panel and F1 score on the right panel) over iterations.
The solid lines show the performance indicators, together with the cross-validation generalization error.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The cross-validation performance is stable across iterations.
This is expected as the classifiers learn from the same data on which the generalization is estimated — i.e., the classifiers are representative of the data they were trained on.
However, the difference between the test set performance and cross-validation performance is indicative of the representativity over the entire dataset.
The cross-validation accuracy is consistently lower than the test set accuracy because the test data is more imbalanced than labeled data.
The cross-validation F1 is more optimistic than the test set F1.
Finally, the difference between the two stabilizes for the later iterations, further suggesting the convergence.
&lt;img src="fig3.png" alt="Convergence of topic classifier performances over seven iterations.">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="applying-the-qualitative-mapping">Applying the Qualitative Mapping&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We employ the obtained augmented labeled set to analyze the dynamics of problematic opinions at scale.
We machine-label the opinions in a large set of postings spanning over a long time, allowing us to apply the qualitative-defined coding schema to a significantly larger sample of postings.
This reduces the unavoidable selection bias of the deep qualitative study.
It also offers a critical tool for analyzing co-occurring opinions, which helps identify central opinions.
It is common for postings to express multiple opinions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We explore central opinions by building an opinion co-occurrence network in the online conversation of the topic &lt;strong>2019-20 Australian bushfire season&lt;/strong>.
In the network, nodes are the opinions captured during the bushfire conversation, while edges are present when both opinions are detected in the same postings.
The node degree of a given opinion node represents the number of opinions that co-occurred with it.
The edges are weighted by the number of postings in which their connected node opinions co-occurred.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The following plot presents each edge's daily proportions of weights among all edges between September 2019 and January 2020.
We show six edges (i.e., opinion pairs) to represent three types of temporal dynamics:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A continuous and relatively strong association between prevalent opinions — &amp;ldquo;Climate change crisis isn't real&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Climate change is a UN hoax,&amp;rdquo; which not notably is a conspiracy theory.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Associations with declining relative frequencies — &amp;ldquo;Greta Thunberg should not have a platform or influence as a climate&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Women and girls don't deserve a voice in the public sphere&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Rising associations such as &amp;ldquo;bushfires and climate change not related&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;bushfires were caused by random arsonists&amp;rdquo;; and also the conspiracy theory associations between &amp;ldquo;United Nations is corrupt&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;United Nations wants to be the global ruling government&amp;rdquo;.
&lt;img src="fig2.png" alt="Daily proportions of edge weights of six selected co-occurred opinions pairs.">&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>In the following plot, we map the co-occurrence network from posts published over 14 days in late September 2019, i.e., the period when the betweenness for conspiracy opinions is at peak.
This figure explains the ambivalent network role that conspiracy opinions can play: we first note a conspiracy opinion with relatively high degree and frequency — &amp;ldquo;Climate change is a UN hoax&amp;rdquo; —, while we also observe the presence of low degree but high betweenness conspiracy opinions at the periphery of the network — &amp;ldquo;Bushfires linked to secret elites&amp;rsquo; secret technology (chemtrails, HAARP, HSRN, geoengineering)&amp;quot;, &amp;ldquo;bushfires deliberately lit to promote a climate change agenda&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Australia should not be a member of the United Nations&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="featured.png" alt="A visualization of the co-occurrence network in late September 2020 — node sizes and colors indicate the degrees and betweenness values">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="references">References&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>[1] Jack, C. 2017. Lexicon of lies: Terms for problematic information. Data &amp;amp; Society.&lt;br>
[2] Posetti, J.; and Bontcheva, K. 2020. Disinfodemic: deciphering COVID-19 disinformation. Policy brief 1.&lt;br>
[3] Ram, R.; Kong, Q.; and Rizoiu, M.-A. 2021. Birdspotter: A Tool for Analyzing and Labeling Twitter Users. In WSDM. ACM.&lt;br>
[4] Smith, N.; and Graham, T. 2019. Mapping the anti-vaccination movement on Facebook. Information, Communication &amp;amp; Society.&lt;br>
[5] Molina, M. D.; Sundar, S. S.; Le, T.; and Lee, D. 2019. “Fake news” is not simply false information: a concept explication and taxonomy of online content. American behavioral scientist&lt;br>
[6] Glaeser, E. L.; and Sunstein, C. R. 2009. Extremism and social learning. Journal of Legal Analysis.&lt;br>
[7] Vaswani, A.; Shazeer, N.; Parmar, N.; Uszkoreit, J.; Jones, L.; Gomez, A. N.; Kaiser, L.; and Polosukhin, I. 2017. Attention is all you need. In NeurIPS.&lt;br>
[8] Liu, Y.; Ott, M.; Goyal, N.; Du, J.; Joshi, M.; Chen, D.; Levy, O.; Lewis, M.; Zettlemoyer, L.; and Stoyanov, V. 2019. Roberta: A robustly optimized BERT pretraining approach. arXiv.&lt;br>
[9] Settles, B. 2012. Active learning. Synthesis lectures on artificial intelligence and machine learning.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Discovering coordinated disinformation via Hawkes processes</title><link>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/theme2_content/coordinated_disinfo_hawkes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/theme2_content/coordinated_disinfo_hawkes/</guid><description>&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/kzGkvZRjnoI?start=70" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;p>Recording of the presentation &amp;ldquo;Discovering the Strategies and Promotion Schedules of Coordinated Disinformation via Hawkes Intensity Processes&amp;rdquo; (Tim Graham, &lt;strong>Marian-Andrei Rizoiu&lt;/strong>, Axel Bruns, Dan Angus), presented at the &lt;a href="https://www.ecrea2021.eu/">European Communication Conference (ECREA) 2021&lt;/a>, 8 Sep. 2021.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="discovering-the-strategies-and-promotion-schedules-of-coordinated-disinformation-via-hawkes-intensity-processes">Discovering the Strategies and Promotion Schedules of Coordinated Disinformation via Hawkes Intensity Processes&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.qut.edu.au/about/our-people/academic-profiles/timothy.graham">Tim Graham&lt;/a>, Digital Media Research Centre, Queensland University of Technology&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://www.behavioral-ds.science/authors/ma-rizoiu/">Marian-Andrei Rizoiu&lt;/a>, Data Science Institute, University of Technology Sydney&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://www.qut.edu.au/about/our-people/academic-profiles/a.bruns">Axel Bruns&lt;/a>, Digital Media Research Centre, Queensland University of Technology&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://www.qut.edu.au/about/our-people/academic-profiles/daniel.angus">Dan Angus&lt;/a>, Digital Media Research Centre, Queensland University of Technology&lt;/p>
&lt;p>‘Fake news’ and broader ‘information disorders’ [6] such as mis- and disinformation have emerged as global issues that threaten to undermine democracy and authentic political communication on social media [1]. Increasingly sophisticated coordination strategies have intensified the scale and scope of the impact that disinformation has on public opinion and democratic trust. Howard et al. [3] found that coordinated disinformation operations are now occurring in 48 countries, and in 2019 the European External Action Service detected and exposed over 1,000 cases of disinformation within the European Union [2]. Whilst disinformation has attracted much scholarly attention, most studies to date have focussed on the diffusion and impact of individual content (e.g. ‘fake news’ articles) and the activity of individual accounts (e.g. bots and trolls).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>An emerging problem is to understand message coordination strategies, where content authored and distributed by agents (e.g. Twitter trolls) is governed and scheduled by some unknown principal actor [4]. We know that coordinated promotion (e.g. sharing, liking, retweeting) of ‘fake news’ articles by trolls and social bots can greatly increase and amplify the negative effects of these attempts to sow discord and manipulate public conversations about election candidates and partisan issues such as immigration and climate change. Likewise, it is evident that disinformation campaigns unfold via ‘collaborative work’ that co-opts and cultivates organic systems in order to produce desired effects such as increased polarisation, distrust in news media and confusion of the audience [7]. This makes identifying ‘inauthentic’ versus ‘organic’ activity ever more difficult, as they are intricately enmeshed in real-world disinformation campaigns.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this paper, we tackle the problem of inferring the coordinated promotion schedules of ‘fake news’ articles using a novel approach known as Hawkes Intensity Processes (HIP; see [5]). We analyse the diffusion of articles from ten major sources of hyperpartisan information and ‘fake news’ within over 16.5 million tweets that linked to content from these sites during July to September 2019. Using HIP, we uncover not only coordination strategies but also the promotion schedules of ‘fake news’ content, where agents (in this case Twitter accounts) are being centrally managed by principals (e.g. state operatives, government officials, etc.) in order to strategically promote ‘fake news’ content and maximise its virality and longevity in the social memory. This paper provides preliminary results from this ongoing research, highlighting the current challenges as well as open problems and gaps for future work.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="references">References&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>[1] Benkler, Y., Faris, R., &amp;amp; Roberts, H. (2018). Network propaganda: Manipulation, disinformation, and radicalization in American politics. Oxford University Press.&lt;br>
[2] European Commission. (2019). Action plan against disinformation: Report in progress. Retrieved 20 November 2019 from: &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/commission/sites/beta-political/files/factsheet_disinfo_elex_140619_final.pdf">https://ec.europa.eu/commission/sites/beta-political/files/factsheet_disinfo_elex_140619_final.pdf&lt;/a>.&lt;br>
[3] Howard, P. N., &amp;amp; Kollanyi, B. (2016). Bots, #StrongerIn, and #Brexit: Computational Propaganda during the UK-EU Referendum. SSRN Electronic Journal. doi:10.2139/ssrn.2798311&lt;br>
[4] Keller, F. B., Schoch, D., Stier, S., &amp;amp; Yang, J. (2019). Political Astroturfing on Twitter: How to Coordinate a Disinformation Campaign. Political Communication, 1-25.&lt;br>
[5] Rizoiu, M. A., Xie, L., Sanner, S., Cebrian, M., Yu, H., &amp;amp; Van Hentenryck, P. (2017, April). Expecting to be hip: Hawkes intensity processes for social media popularity. In Proceedings of the 26th International Conference on World Wide Web (pp. 735-744). International World Wide Web Conferences Steering Committee.&lt;br>
[6] Wardle, C., &amp;amp; Derakhshan, H. (2017). Information disorder: Toward an interdisciplinary framework for research and policymaking. Council of Europe Report DGI (2017) 09.&lt;br>
[7] Wilson, T., Zhou, K., &amp;amp; Starbird, K. (2018). Assembling Strategic Narratives: Information Operations as Collaborative Work within an Online Community. Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction, 2(CSCW), 183.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-panel-coordinated-inauthentic-behaviour-in-social-media-new-methods-and-findings">The panel: &amp;ldquo;Coordinated Inauthentic Behaviour in Social Media: New Methods and Findings&amp;rdquo;&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="panel-rationale">Panel Rationale&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Social media platforms are increasingly forced to address what Facebook now describes as ‘coordinated inauthentic behaviour’ (Gleicher 2018): online influence operations that seek to trick platform algorithms into promoting and recommending ‘problematic information’ (Jack 2017), to mislead the human users of such platforms into accepting and sharing such content, and thereby also to affect broader issue frames and news agendas in mainstream media coverage. Concerns about such coordinated inauthentic behaviour extend earlier fears about the influence of malignant social bots, but also transcend them: drawing on social bots as well as human labour, coordinated inauthentic behaviour is likely to involve a combination of manual and automated activity. This additional human factor also complicates the detection of such coordinated activities, and their distinction from genuine, organic, authentic coordinated actions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This cross-national and interdisciplinary panel approaches the study of coordinated inauthentic behaviour from a number of directions. It outlines novel and innovative detection and analysis approaches for a number of leading social media platforms, and presents their results in the context of domestic and international political debates across several national contexts. Further, it also considers how mainstream journalism might report on and respond to such activities in order to protect news audiences from being affected by coordinated inauthentic behaviours.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first two papers in this panel focus especially on coordinated inauthentic link-sharing practices. Paper 1 introduces Hawkes Intensity Processes (HIP), a novel technique for inferring the coordinated content promotion schedules of automated social media accounts, and applies this to a major dataset of 16.5 million tweets containing links to ten major sites identified as sources of hyperpartisan content and ‘fake news’. In doing so, it uncovers new networks of inauthentic Twitter actors. Paper 2 investigates similar coordinated link-sharing activity on Facebook in Italy during the 2018 Italian and 2019 European elections. It uncovers evidence for the involvement of dozens of pages, groups, and public profiles in such media manipulation attempts. Paper 3 complements this work by focussing especially on the temporal posting patterns in such coordinated activity. It employs the recurrence plotting technique to identify traces of inauthentic actors’ use of automated scheduling tools in systematically posting content to a network of apparently unrelated pages, focussing here especially on a group of far-right pages on Facebook. Paper 4 examines ten coordinated disinformation campaigns across the globe (e.g., Hong Kong, Russia, USA, Spain and Germany) and identifies important traits that help distinguish between those participating in the disinformation campaign and the regular users they try to imitate. Paper 5, finally, shifts our attention to a core target of such coordinated inauthentic behaviour: the journalists and editors whose perception of current political moods such influence operations often aim to affect. Drawing on a series of in-depth interviews with Danish news workers and related stakeholders, it examines their understanding of and responses to coordinated mis- and disinformation campaigns.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Collectively, these studies contribute substantially to advancing the methodological toolkit and extending the empirical evidence base for the study of coordinated inauthentic behaviour, while also not losing sight of the stakeholders that such work seeks to support. They offer an independent assessment of the nature and extent of the problem across several leading social media platforms, complementing the platform providers’ own investigations into such activities and identifying possible responses to such concerns for both social and mainstream media actors.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="the-papers-presented-are-presenters-bolded">The papers presented are (presenters bolded):&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Discovering the Strategies and Promotion Schedules of Coordinated Disinformation via Hawkes Intensity Processes (Tim Graham, &lt;strong>Marian-Andrei Rizoiu&lt;/strong>, Axel Bruns, Dan Angus)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It Takes a Village to Manipulate the Media: Coordinated Link Sharing Behaviour during 2018 and 2019 Italian Elections (&lt;strong>Fabio Giglietto&lt;/strong>, Nicola Righetti, Luca Rossi, Giada Marino)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Recurrence Plotting for Detecting Duplicate Online Posting Activities (&lt;strong>Dan Angus&lt;/strong>, Tim Graham, Tobias Keller, Brenda Moon, Axel Bruns)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Astroturfing in Hong Kong and Elsewhere: Patterns of Coordination in Hidden Twitter Campaigns (&lt;strong>Franziska B. Keller&lt;/strong>, Sebastian Stier, David Schoch, JungHwan Yang)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>birdspotter: A toolkit for analyzing and labelling Twitter users</title><link>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/theme2_content/birdspotter/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/theme2_content/birdspotter/</guid><description>&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/52HwHAiK1rs" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;!-- &lt;img src="https://www.behavioral-ds.science/img/birdspotter_logo.png" alt="Birdspotter Logo" width="200"/> -->
&lt;!-- Motivation -->
&lt;!-- Framing: Problem -> Solution -->
&lt;!-- Context -->
&lt;p>Social media platforms, although relatively new, host millions of users and billions of interactions daily. As tied as we are to these platforms, they profoundly impact our social institutions through phenomena such as disinformation, political polarization, and social bots.&lt;/p>
&lt;!-- Problem -->
&lt;p>Researchers are increasingly interested in trying to form an understanding of phenomena and their implications. Social scientists, political scientists, and data practitioners alike curate expansive datasets to combat these potentially adverse effects on our society; however, they lack the appropriate tooling.&lt;/p>
&lt;!-- Solution -->
&lt;p>&lt;code>birdspotter&lt;/code> is an &lt;strong>easy-to-use&lt;/strong> tool that models Twitter users&amp;rsquo; attributes and labels them. It comes prepackaged with a &lt;strong>state-of-the-art bot detector&lt;/strong> and an &lt;strong>influence quantification&lt;/strong> system based on tweet dynamics. &lt;code>birdspotter&lt;/code> features a generalized user labeler, which can be retrained easily with the engineered features to address a variety of use cases. Also, &lt;a href="http://birdspotter.ml/">birdspotter.ml&lt;/a> is a web application that can be utilized to explore datasets and derive a narrative around a dataset.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this post, I'll showcase the basic usage of &lt;code>birdspotter&lt;/code> and &lt;a href="http://birdspotter.ml/">birdspotter.ml&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="installation">Installation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The package can be installed in the canonical python way:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-{bash}">pip install birdspotter
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;h2 id="getting-a-dataset">Getting a dataset&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The Twitter T&amp;amp;Cs restrict the sharing of tweet data directly online; however, they do allow the sharing of tweet-ids, which can be converted to full tweet data through a process called &lt;em>hydration&lt;/em>. Tools like &lt;a href="https://github.com/DocNow/twarc">twarc&lt;/a> can be used to hydrate a Tweet ID dataset. The resulting dataset will be in &lt;code>jsonl&lt;/code> (line delimited &lt;code>json&lt;/code>) format, which &lt;code>birdspotter&lt;/code> accepts directly.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the below examples, we use two datasets; a collection of COVID-19 related tweets from January 31st, 2020 [1], and a collection of tweets about politicians on Twitter [2].&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The politicians&amp;rsquo; dataset was acquired through the following process (and a similar process was taken for the COVID-19 dataset):&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-{bash}">pip install twarc
wget http://twitterpoliticians.org./downloads/base/all_tweet_ids.csv
twarc hydrate all_tweet_ids.csv &amp;gt; tweets.jsonl
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;h2 id="basic-usage">Basic Usage&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The code below imports the main class &lt;code>Birdspotter&lt;/code>, extracts the tweets from their standard format, labels the users with the default bot detector and influence, and reformats the retweet cascades into a tidier format.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-{python}">## Import birdspotter
from birdspotter import BirdSpotter
## Extracts the tweets from the raw jsonl [https://github.com/echen102/COVID-19-TweetIDs]
bs = BirdSpotter('covid19.jsonl')
## Uses the default bot labeller and influence quantification systems
bs.getLabeledUsers()
## Formats the retweet cascades, such that expected retweet structures can extracted
bs.getCascadesDataFrame()
## Access the botness labels and influence scores
bs.featureDataframe[['botness', 'influence']]
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>From here, the dataset is readily profile-able:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-{python}">botness_dist = sns.histplot(data=bs.featureDataframe, x=&amp;quot;botness&amp;quot;)
influence_eccdf = sns.ecdfplot(data=bs.featureDataframe, x=&amp;quot;influence&amp;quot;, complementary=True).set(xscale=&amp;quot;log&amp;quot;, yscale=&amp;quot;log&amp;quot;)
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.behavioral-ds.science/img/covid_profile.png" alt="COVID Dataset Profile: (Left) The distribution of bot scores of users; (Right) The ECCDF of influence scores of users, showing a long-tailed (rich-gets-richer) paradigm">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-visualizer">The visualizer&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>An alternative way to profile a dataset is the use &lt;a href="http://birdspotter.ml">&lt;code>birdspotter.ml&lt;/code>&lt;/a>, which facilitates dataset exploration and narrative construction.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.behavioral-ds.science/img/auspol_teaser.png" alt="birdspotter.ml visualizer: The various components shown include the scatterplot panel (Left), the user information panel (Top Right), and the retweet cascades panel (Bottom Right)">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The visualizer features a scatterplot (on the left) of influence and botness for a sample of users and the population density. The colors represent the hashtags (a proxy for the topic) that the users most tweet about in the dataset. Users within the scatterplot are hoverable and selectable, and their information populates in the components on the right.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The top right component shows information and metrics about the selected user and links the user's profile.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The bottom right component shows the retweet cascades where a user has participated and highlights their participation. The points represent the follower counts (social capital) of users and their retweets/tweets&amp;rsquo; timing. The points are also hoverable and selectable.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="customising-the-labeller">Customising the labeller&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>By default, the labeler is trained as a bot detection system, comparable to the state-of-the-art &lt;a href="https://botometer.osome.iu.edu/">&lt;code>botometer&lt;/code>&lt;/a>. Notable, &lt;code>birdspotter&lt;/code> is provided in an offline package and can be applied at scale, while &lt;code>botometer&lt;/code> is accessible only via an online API, which is often prohibitively rate-limited.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;code>birdspotter&lt;/code> is a versatile tool and can be utilized by practitioners for a variety of use-cases. For example, we could train the labeler to identify political leaning. This process is a bit involved, so we summarise it below;&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>We hydrate some tweets from the Twitter Parlimentarian Database&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We filter the tweets to include only &lt;strong>Australian Politicians&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We &lt;strong>label right-wing partied politicians positively&lt;/strong>, and others negatively (with &lt;code>bs_pol.getBotAnnotationTemplate&lt;/code> for example)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We &lt;strong>retrain &lt;code>birdspotter&lt;/code>&lt;/strong> with these new labels and label all users (i.e., including users the politicians retweeted) using the new model&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;!-- ```{python class.source = 'fold-hide'} -->
&lt;!-- # This is the guts of the code; it does what is described above -->
&lt;!-- politicians = pd.read_csv('./full_member_info.csv', encoding='utf16') -->
&lt;!-- politicians_aus = politicians[politicians['country'] == 'Australia'] -->
&lt;!-- politicians_aus_available = politicians_aus[~politicians_aus['uid'].isnull()] -->
&lt;!-- def classify_party(party_id): -->
&lt;!-- mapping = { -->
&lt;!-- 464 : 1, # Liberal Party of Australia -->
&lt;!-- 465 : -1, # Australian Labor Party -->
&lt;!-- 467 : 1, # The Nationals -->
&lt;!-- 468 : 0, # Nick Xenophon Team -->
&lt;!-- 469 : -1, # Australian Greens -->
&lt;!-- 471 : np.nan, -->
&lt;!-- 475 : 1, # Katter's Australian Party -->
&lt;!-- } -->
&lt;!-- return mapping[party_id] -->
&lt;!-- politicians_aus_available['isright'] = politicians_aus_available['party_id'].apply(classify_party) -->
&lt;!-- politicians_aus_available['user_id'] = politicians_aus_available['uid'].astype(int).astype(str) -->
&lt;!-- politicians_aus_available = politicians_aus_available.set_index('user_id') -->
&lt;!-- with open('./tweets.jsonl', 'r') as rf, open('./aus_tweets.jsonl', 'w') as wf: -->
&lt;!-- for line in tqdm(rf): -->
&lt;!-- try: -->
&lt;!-- j = json.loads(line) -->
&lt;!-- if j['user']['id_str'] in politicians_aus_available['uid'].astype(int).astype(str).values: -->
&lt;!-- wf.write(json.dumps(j) + '\n') -->
&lt;!-- except Exception as e: -->
&lt;!-- print(j) -->
&lt;!-- print(e) -->
&lt;!-- break -->
&lt;!-- bs = BirdSpotter('aus_tweets.jsonl') -->
&lt;!-- bs.getLabeledUsers() -->
&lt;!-- bs.getCascadesDataFrame() -->
&lt;!-- with open('bs_aus_module.pk', 'wb') as wf: -->
&lt;!-- pk.dump(bs,wf, protocol=4) -->
&lt;!-- bs.featureDataframe['isright'] = politicians_aus_available['isright'] -->
&lt;!-- ground_truth = bs.featureDataframe[~bs.featureDataframe['isright'].isnull()][['isright']] -->
&lt;!-- ground_truth['isbot'] = ground_truth['isright'] == 1 -->
&lt;!-- ground_truth = ground_truth[~ground_truth.index.duplicated()] -->
&lt;!-- data = bs.featureDataframe.copy()[bs.featureDataframe.index.isin(ground_truth.index)] -->
&lt;!-- data = data[~data.index.duplicated()] -->
&lt;!-- del data['isright'] -->
&lt;!-- del data['botness'] -->
&lt;!-- del data['influence'] -->
&lt;!-- del data['cascade_membership'] -->
&lt;!-- data = data[list(data.columns[data.dtypes != 'object'])] -->
&lt;!-- data['isbot'] = ground_truth['isbot'].loc[data.index] -->
&lt;!-- with open('pol_training_data.pickle', 'wb') as wf: -->
&lt;!-- pk.dump(data,wf, protocol=4) -->
&lt;!-- from birdspotter import BirdSpotter -->
&lt;!-- import pickle as pk -->
&lt;!-- # bs_pol = BirdSpotter('aus_tweets.jsonl') -->
&lt;!-- with open('bs_aus_module.pk', 'rb') as rf: -->
&lt;!-- bs_pol = pk.load(rf) -->
&lt;!-- print("Loaded module") -->
&lt;!-- bs_pol.trainClassifierModel('pol_training_data.pickle') -->
&lt;!-- print("finished training") -->
&lt;!-- del bs_pol.featureDataframe['botness'] -->
&lt;!-- print("removed botness column") -->
&lt;!-- bs_pol.getBotness() -->
&lt;!-- bs_pol.getLabeledUsers() -->
&lt;!-- print("got labels") -->
&lt;!-- with open('pol_booster.pickle', 'wb') as wf: -->
&lt;!-- pk.dump(bs_pol.booster, wf, protocol=4) -->
&lt;!-- print("pickled booster") -->
&lt;!-- with open('aus_pol_bs_module.pickle', 'wb') as wf: -->
&lt;!-- pk.dump(bs_pol, wf, protocol=4) -->
&lt;!-- with open('pol_booster.pickle', 'wb') as wf: -->
&lt;!-- pk.dump(bs.booster, wf, protocol=4) -->
&lt;!-- ``` -->
&lt;!-- This is context: -->
&lt;!-- I want to start with the opportunity namely the analysis of large amounts of population data tranparently showing the interactions and discourse of people, allowing practictioners to model important applications in society. I also want to highlight the research issues which require investigation, namely social bots, misinformation, polarization, etc. -->
&lt;!-- This is content -->
&lt;!-- I then want to move into the problem, namely that there is a lack of tooling to analyse these huge swaths of data -->
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-{python}">bs_pol = BirdSpotter('aus_tweets.jsonl')
bs_pol.trainClassifierModel('pol_training_data.pickle')
bs_pol.getLabeledUsers()
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>On this limited of Australian politicians dataset, a 10-fold CV of &lt;code>birdspotter&lt;/code> garners an average AUC (Area under ROC) of 0.986.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;code>birdspotter&lt;/code> aims to democratize social analyzes that were once the domain of machine learning experts, generating insights and understanding of online phenomena and mitigating their potentially adverse effects on our society. This post shows how &lt;code>birdspotter&lt;/code> can be used in both a simple and advanced way to recover such insights.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="references">References&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>[1] Chen, E. et al. 2020. Tracking social media discourse about the covid-19 pandemic: Development of a public coronavirus twitter data set. JMIR Public Health and Surveillance. 6, 2 (2020), e19273.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>[2] Vliet, L. van et al. 2020. The twitter parliamentarian database: Analyzing twitter politics across 26 countries. PloS one. 15, 9 (2020), e0237073.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>User Analysis on reshare cascades about COVID-19</title><link>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/theme2_content/user_analysis/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/theme2_content/user_analysis/</guid><description>&lt;p>We demonstrate in this blog post a tutorial on applying the tools for analyzing online information diffusions about Twitter users, &lt;a href="https://github.com/behavioral-ds/BirdSpotter">&lt;code>birdspotter&lt;/code>&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://github.com/behavioral-ds/evently">&lt;code>evently&lt;/code>&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="dataset">Dataset&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In this tutorial, we apply two tools for analyzing Twitter users, on a COVID-19 retweet dataset. The dataset
is curated by Chen, et al. One can obtain a copy of the tweet IDs from
their &lt;a href="https://github.com/echen102/COVID-19-TweetIDs">project&lt;/a>. We
only use the 31st of Janury sample of the whole dataset for
demonstration purpose. The tweets can be recovered by &lt;code>hydration&lt;/code>
from their IDs. We note that some tweets might have been deleted and in
the end we manage to get 69.2% (1,489,877) of the original tweets.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="tools">Tools&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>While &lt;code>BirdSpotter&lt;/code> captures the social influence and botness of Twitter
users, &lt;code>evently&lt;/code> specifically models the temporal dynamics of online
information diffusion. We leverage information provided by the tools to
study the users in the COVID19 dataset.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-r">library(evently)
library(reticulate)
birdspotter &amp;lt;- import('birdspotter')
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;h2 id="preprocessing-tweets">Preprocessing tweets&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>At this step, we seek to extract diffusion cascades from the &lt;code>COVID-19&lt;/code>
dataset for analyzing user influence and botness. A diffusion cascade
consist of an initial tweet posted by a Twitter user and followed then
by a sereis of retweets. A function provided by &lt;code>evently&lt;/code> allows one to
obtain cascades from JSON formatted raw tweets. On the other hand, we
initialize a &lt;code>BirdSpotter&lt;/code> instance and compute the influence and
botness scores for all users in the
dataset.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-r">cascades &amp;lt;- parse_raw_tweets_to_cascades('corona_2020_01_31.jsonl', keep_user = T, keep_absolute_time = T)
bs &amp;lt;- birdspotter$BirdSpotter('corona_2020_01_31.jsonl')
labeled_users &amp;lt;- bs$getLabeledUsers()[, c('user_id', 'botness', 'influence')]
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>As we cannot publish &lt;code>corona_2020_01_31.jsonl&lt;/code> due to Twitter TOC, we
have stored the results and load them below&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-r">load('corona_2020_01_31.rda')
labeled_users &amp;lt;- read.csv('corona_31_botness_influence.csv', stringsAsFactors = F,
colClasses=c(&amp;quot;character&amp;quot;,rep(&amp;quot;numeric&amp;quot;,3)))
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>We note that all user IDs have been encrypted. After obtaining the
results, let’s first conduct some simple measurements on users and
cascades.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-r">library(ggplot2)
# check the density of these two values
mean_bot &amp;lt;- mean(labeled_users$botness, na.rm = T)
ggplot(labeled_users, aes(botness)) +
stat_density(geom = 'line') +
geom_vline(xintercept = mean_bot, linetype=2, color = 'red') +
geom_text(data=data.frame(), aes(x = mean_bot, y = 2, label= sprintf('mean: %s', round(mean_bot, 2))), color= 'red', angle=90, vjust=-0.11)
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="README_files/figure-gfm/unnamed-chunk-4-1.png" alt="">&lt;!-- -->&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-r">mean_inf &amp;lt;- mean(labeled_users$influence)
ggplot(labeled_users) +
stat_ecdf(aes(influence, 1 - ..y..)) +
scale_x_log10() +
scale_y_log10() +
ylab('CCDF') +
geom_vline(xintercept = mean_inf, linetype=2, color = 'red') +geom_text(data=data.frame(), aes(x = mean_inf, y = 1e-3, label= sprintf('mean: %s', round(mean_inf, 2))), color= 'red', angle=90, vjust=-0.11)
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>## Warning: Transformation introduced infinite values in continuous y-axis
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="README_files/figure-gfm/unnamed-chunk-4-2.png" alt="">&lt;!-- -->&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-r">mean_value &amp;lt;- mean(sapply(cascades, nrow))
ggplot(data.frame(size = sapply(cascades, nrow))) +
stat_ecdf(aes(size, 1 - ..y..)) +
scale_x_log10() + scale_y_log10() +
geom_vline(xintercept = mean_value, linetype=2, color = 'red') +
geom_text(data=data.frame(), aes(x = mean_value, y = 1e-3, label= sprintf('mean: %s', round(mean_value, 2))), color= 'red', angle=90, vjust=-0.11) +
xlab('cascade size') +
ylab('CCDF')
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>## Warning: Transformation introduced infinite values in continuous y-axis
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="README_files/figure-gfm/unnamed-chunk-4-3.png" alt="">&lt;!-- -->&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-r">mean_value2 &amp;lt;- mean(sapply(cascades, function(c) c$time[nrow(c)]))
ggplot(data.frame(time = sapply(cascades, function(c) c$time[nrow(c)]))) +
stat_ecdf(aes(time, 1 - ..y..)) +
scale_x_continuous(trans = 'log1p', breaks = c(0, 100, 10000, 1000000), labels = c('0', '1e2', '1e4', '1e6')) +
scale_y_log10() +
geom_vline(xintercept = mean_value2, linetype=2, color = 'red') +
geom_text(data=data.frame(), aes(x = mean_value2, y = 1e-3, label= sprintf('mean: %s', round(mean_value2, 2))), color= 'red', angle=90, vjust=-0.11) +
xlab('cascade final event time')+
ylab('CCDF')
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>## Warning: Transformation introduced infinite values in continuous y-axis
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="README_files/figure-gfm/unnamed-chunk-4-4.png" alt="">&lt;!-- -->&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-r">mean_value &amp;lt;- mean(labeled_users$activity)
ggplot(data.frame(size = labeled_users$activity)) +
stat_ecdf(aes(size, 1 - ..y..)) +
scale_x_log10() +
scale_y_log10() +
geom_vline(xintercept = mean_value, linetype=2, color = 'red') +
geom_text(data=data.frame(), aes(x = mean_value, y = 1e-3, label= sprintf('mean: %s', round(mean_value, 2))), color= 'red', angle=90, vjust=-0.11) + xlab('user activity')+ ylab('CCDF')
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>## Warning: Transformation introduced infinite values in continuous y-axis
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="README_files/figure-gfm/unnamed-chunk-4-5.png" alt="">&lt;!-- -->&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="retrain-the-bot-detector">Retrain the bot detector&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If one find the botness scores are not accurate, &lt;code>birdspotter&lt;/code> provides
a relabeling tool and a retrain API to learn from the given relabeled
dataset&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-r"># output a file for mannual labeling
bs$getBotAnnotationTemplate('users_to_label.csv')
# Once annotated the botness detector can be trained with
bs$trainClassifierModel('users_to_label.csv')
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;h2 id="fit-user-posted-cacsades-with-evently">Fit user posted cacsades with &lt;code>evently&lt;/code>&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We model a group of cascades initiated by a particular user jointly and
treat the fitted model as a characterization of the user. In this
example, we select two users for comparison.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-r">selected_users &amp;lt;- c('369686755237813560', '174266868073402929')
# fit Hawkes process on cascades initiated by the selected users
user_cascades_fitted &amp;lt;- lapply(selected_users, function(user) {
# select cascades that are initiated by the &amp;quot;selected_user&amp;quot;
selected_cascades &amp;lt;- Filter(function(cascade) cascade$user[[1]] == user, cascades)
# obtain the observation times;
# note 1580515200 is 1st Feb when the observation stopped
# as we only observed until the end of 31st Jan
times &amp;lt;- 1580515200 - sapply(selected_cascades, function(cas) cas$absolute_time[1])
# fit a model on the selected cascades;
fit_series(data = selected_cascades, model_type = 'mPL', observation_time = times, cores = 10)
})
user_cascades_SEISMIC_fitted &amp;lt;- lapply(selected_users, function(user) {
selected_cascades &amp;lt;- Filter(function(cascade) cascade$user[[1]] == user, cascades)
times &amp;lt;- 1580515200 - sapply(selected_cascades, function(cas) cas$absolute_time[1])
fit_series(data = selected_cascades, model_type = 'SEISMIC',
observation_time = times)
})
# check the fitted kernel functions
plot_kernel_function(user_cascades_fitted) +
scale_color_discrete(labels = c(&amp;quot;@BobOngHugots&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;@Jaefans_Global&amp;quot;))
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="README_files/figure-gfm/unnamed-chunk-6-1.png" alt="">&lt;!-- -->&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The plot shows the fitted kernel functions of these two users which
reflect their time-decaying influence of attracting followers to reshare
their posts. We then demonstrate how to simulate new cascades&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-r">set.seed(134841)
user_magnitude &amp;lt;- Filter(function(cascade) cascade$user[[1]] == selected_users[[1]], cascades)[[1]]$magnitude[1]
# simulate a new cascade from @BobOngHugots
sim_cascade &amp;lt;- generate_series(user_cascades_fitted[[1]], M = user_magnitude)
plot_event_series(cascade = sim_cascade, model = user_cascades_fitted[[1]])
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="README_files/figure-gfm/unnamed-chunk-7-1.png" alt="">&lt;!-- -->&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-r">selected_cascade &amp;lt;- Filter(function(cascade) cascade$user[1] == selected_users[[1]], cascades)[[1]]
selected_time &amp;lt;- user_cascades_fitted[[1]]$observation_time[1]
# simulate a cascade with a &amp;quot;selected_cascade&amp;quot; from @BobOngHugots
sim_cascade &amp;lt;- generate_series(user_cascades_fitted[[1]], M = user_magnitude,
init_history = selected_cascade)
sprintf('%s new events simulated after cascade',
nrow(sim_cascade[[1]]) - nrow(selected_cascade))
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>## [1] &amp;quot;25 new events simulated after cascade&amp;quot;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-r">predict_final_popularity(user_cascades_fitted[[1]],
selected_cascade, selected_time)
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>## [1] 458.303
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-r"># predict with SEISMIC model, assume we have fitted the SEISMIC model
predict_final_popularity(user_cascades_SEISMIC_fitted[[1]],
selected_cascade, selected_time)
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>## [1] 729.923
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-r">get_branching_factor(user_cascades_fitted[[1]])
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>## [1] 0.7681281
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-r">get_viral_score(user_cascades_fitted[[1]])
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>## [1] 7.407763
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;h2 id="visualize-users-in-a-latent-space">Visualize users in a latent space&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We show a visualization of top 300 users posted most tweets using the
features returned by &lt;code>evently&lt;/code> along with the botness and influence
scores from &lt;code>birdspotter&lt;/code>.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-r"># obtain observation times here again
times &amp;lt;- 1580515200 - sapply(cascades, function(cas) cas$absolute_time[1])
# indicate the grouping of each cascade with the user who started the cascade
names(cascades) &amp;lt;- sapply(cascades, function(cas) cas$user[1])
# fit Hawkes processes on all cascades first
fitted_corona &amp;lt;- group_fit_series(cascades, model_type = 'mPL', observation_time = times)
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>The fitting procedure takes quite long so we again load the pre-fitted
models here&lt;/p>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-r">load('fitted_models.rda')
# choose the top 300 users who started most cacsades
selected_users &amp;lt;- labeled_users$user_id[labeled_users$user_id %in%
names(sort(sapply(fitted_corona, length), decreasing = T)[seq(300)])]
# gather the stats for these users
user_influences &amp;lt;- labeled_users$influence[labeled_users$user_id %in% selected_users]
user_botness &amp;lt;- labeled_users$botness[labeled_users$user_id %in% selected_users]
fitted_corona_selected &amp;lt;- fitted_corona[selected_users]
# get the features
features &amp;lt;- generate_features(fitted_corona_selected)
# compute distances between users using manhattan distance
features &amp;lt;- features[, -1] # remove the user id column
distances &amp;lt;- dist(features, method = 'manhattan')
library(tsne)
positions &amp;lt;- tsne(distances, k = 2)
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code>## sigma summary: Min. : 0.34223375605395 |1st Qu. : 0.457223801885988 |Median : 0.489891425900637 |Mean : 0.500483006369232 |3rd Qu. : 0.538593613780411 |Max. : 0.676779919259545 |
## Epoch: Iteration #100 error is: 14.1961110881254
## Epoch: Iteration #200 error is: 0.490122133064818
## Epoch: Iteration #300 error is: 0.474257867010761
## Epoch: Iteration #400 error is: 0.472067779170087
## Epoch: Iteration #500 error is: 0.471844181155159
## Epoch: Iteration #600 error is: 0.471798834134577
## Epoch: Iteration #700 error is: 0.471783207059971
## Epoch: Iteration #800 error is: 0.471632929621924
## Epoch: Iteration #900 error is: 0.47087861882558
## Epoch: Iteration #1000 error is: 0.470873765976829
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;pre>&lt;code class="language-r">df &amp;lt;- data.frame(x = positions[,1], y = positions[,2],
influence = user_influences, botness = user_botness)
df &amp;lt;- cbind(df, data.frame(botornot = ifelse(df$botness &amp;gt; 0.6, 'Bot', 'Not Bot')))
ggplot(df, aes(x, y, color = influence, shape = botornot, size = botornot)) +
geom_point() +
scale_shape_manual(values = c(15,1)) +
scale_size_manual(values = c(1.5, 1.2)) +
scale_color_gradient(low = '#56B1F7', high = '#132B43', trans = 'log10') +
theme_void() + labs(size = NULL, shape = NULL) +
theme(legend.direction = 'horizontal', legend.position = c(0.8, 0.2),
legend.key.size = unit(.3, 'cm'), legend.text = element_text(size = 6),
legend.title = element_text(size = 6), legend.spacing = unit(.05, 'cm'))
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="README_files/figure-gfm/unnamed-chunk-10-1.png" alt="">&lt;!-- -->&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>