<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Research | Behavioral Data Science</title><link>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/categories/research/</link><atom:link href="https://www.behavioral-ds.science/categories/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Research</description><generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/img/logo.png</url><title>Research</title><link>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/categories/research/</link></image><item><title>Slipping to the Extreme: A Mixed-Method to Explain How Extreme Opinions Infiltrate Online Discussions</title><link>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/blogpost/icwsm2022/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/blogpost/icwsm2022/</guid><description>&lt;p>In our &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2109.00302.pdf">recent paper&lt;/a> accepted at ICWSM 2022, we propose a complete solution to accelerate the qualitative analysis of problematic online speech — with a specific focus on opinions emerging from online communities — by leveraging machine learning algorithms.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In 2020, the COVID-19 pandemic alerted the world to complex issues that arise from social media platforms circulating user-generated misinformation, hate speech, and conspiracy theories. There are several primary types of quantitative methods for addressing problematic information, including large-scale monitoring of social media datasets, understanding platforms, users, and networks contributing to the &amp;ldquo;infodemic&amp;rdquo;, and predicting future pathways of information spreading.
These studies provide valuable insights into understanding
how problematic information spreads and detecting which sources are reshared frequently and by which accounts. However, these approaches often have less to say about why certain opinions and views gain traction with vulnerable groups and online communities. Qualitative research methods are well placed to address this gap. They provide rich, contextual insights into the social beliefs, values, and practices of online communities, which shape how information is shared and how opinions are formed.
Nevertheless, a common criticism of qualitative research is that the in-depth knowledge comes at the expense of generating insights of limited representativeness and weak robustness of the findings. Therefore, there is a gap between the depth of insight gained from ethnographic and qualitative approaches and the breadth of knowledge gained from computational methods from data science.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This work aims to fill this gap by proposing a mixed-method approach that brings together qualitative insights, large-scale data collection, and human-in-the-loop machine learning approaches. We apply our method to map both in-depth and in-breadth the problematic information around four topics: &lt;em>2019-20 Australian bushfire season&lt;/em>, &lt;em>Climate change&lt;/em>, &lt;em>COVID-19&lt;/em>, and &lt;em>Vaccination&lt;/em> on three social media platforms (Facebook, Twitter and Youtube).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-proposed-pipeline">The Proposed Pipeline&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="fig1.png" alt="The pipeline of machine learning accelerated qualitative research where the human-in-the-loop machine learning algorithms are employed for dataset augmentation.">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We present a complete solution that bridges and facilitates both qualitative and quantitative analysis for studying problematic online speech.
The pipeline consists of three components:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Deep qualitative study&lt;/strong>: we build a platform based on an open-source tool, &lt;em>Wikibase&lt;/em>, where qualitative and quantitative analysis is conducted. It enables constructing an ontology of problematic online speech by performing the qualitative study, which labels data by topics and builds the vocabulary of opinions simultaneously.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Unlabeled data collection&lt;/strong>: we then collect large-scale raw data using the uncovered vocabulary from the deep qualitative study.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dataset augmentation&lt;/strong>: we employ machine learning algorithms to augment the data labeling process with a human-in-the-loop setting. By adopting the state-of-the-art text classification algorithm, RoBERTa, we first train the classifiers to identify problematic speech on postings annotated by the qualitative researchers. Next, we deploy three strategies to select unlabeled data. The active learning strategy selects the data for which the classifiers are most uncertain. The top-confidence strategy selects data that classifiers are most certain about. The third strategy — the random strategy — randomly samples from unlabeled data. The qualitative researchers then label the sampled data, we introduce the newly labeled data in the ontology, and repeat the procedure iteratively until the predictive performance converges.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="applying-the-qualitative-mapping">Applying the Qualitative Mapping&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We employ the obtained augmented labeled set to analyze the dynamics of problematic opinions at scale. We machine-label the opinions in a large set of postings spanning over a long time period which allows us to apply the qualitative-defined coding schema to a significantly larger sample of postings, therefore reducing the unavoidable selection bias of the deep qualitative study. It also offers a critical tool for analyzing co-occurred opinions which help identify central opinions. It is common when postings express multiple opinions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We explore central opinions by building an opinion co-occurrence network in the online conversation of the topic &lt;strong>2019-20 Australian bushfire season&lt;/strong>. In the network, nodes are the opinions captured during the bushfire conversation, while edges are present when both opinions are detected in the same postings. The node
degree of a given opinion node represents the number of opinions co-occurred with it. The edges are weighted by the number of postings in which their connected node opinions co-occurred.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The following plot presents the daily proportions of weights of each edge among all edges between September 2019 and January 2020. We show six edges (i.e., opinion pairs) to represent three types of temporal dynamics:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A continuous and relatively strong association between prevalent opinions — &amp;ldquo;Climate change crisis isn’t real&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Climate change is a UN hoax&amp;rdquo;, which not notably is a conspiracy theory.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Associations with declining relative frequencies — &amp;ldquo;Greta Thunberg should not have a platform or influence as a climate&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Women and girls don’t deserve a voice in the public sphere&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Rising associations such as &amp;ldquo;bushfires and climate change not related&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;bushfires were caused by random arsonists&amp;rdquo;; and also the conspiracy theory associations between &amp;ldquo;United Nations is corrupt&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;United Nations want to be the global ruling government&amp;rdquo;.
&lt;img src="fig2.png" alt="Daily proportions of edge weights of six selected co-occurred opinions pairs.">&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>In the following plot, we map the co-occurrence network from posts published over 14 days in late September 2019, i.e., the period when the betweenness for conspiracy opinions is at peak. This figure explains the ambivalent network role that conspiracy opinions can play: we first note a conspiracy opinion with relatively high degree and frequency — &amp;ldquo;Climate change is a UN hoax&amp;rdquo; —, while we also observe the presence of low degree but high betweenness conspiracy opinions at the periphery of the network — &amp;ldquo;Bushfires linked to secret elites’ secret technology (chemtrails, HAARP, HSRN, geoengineering)&amp;quot;, &amp;ldquo;bushfires deliberately lit to promote a climate change agenda&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Australia should not be a member of the United Nations&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="featured.png" alt="A visualization of the co-occurrence network in late September 2020 — node sizes and colors indicate the degrees and betweenness values">&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>We spent six years scouring billions of links, and found the web is both expanding and shrinking</title><link>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/blogpost/online_diversity/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/blogpost/online_diversity/</guid><description>&lt;p>The online world is continuously expanding — always aggregating more services, more users and more activity. Last year, the number of websites registered on the &amp;ldquo;.com&amp;rdquo; domain &lt;a href="https://www.verisign.com/en_US/channel-resources/domain-registry-products/zone-file/index.xhtml">surpassed 150,000,000&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, more than a quarter of a century since its first commercial use, the growth of the online world is now slowing down in some key categories.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We conducted a multi-year research project analysing global trends in online diversity and dominance. &lt;a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0249993">Our research&lt;/a>, published in Public Library of Science, is the first to reveal some long-term trends in how businesses compete in the age of the web.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We saw a dramatic consolidation of attention towards a shrinking (but increasingly dominant) group of online organisations. So, while there is still growth in the functions, features and applications offered on the web, the number of entities providing these functions is shrinking.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="web-diversity-nosedives">Web diversity nosedives&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We analysed more than six billion user comments from the social media website Reddit dating back to 2006, as well as 11.8 billion Twitter posts from as far back as 2011. In total, our research used a massive 5.6Tb trove of data from more than a decade of global activity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This dataset was more than four times the size of the original data from the Hubble Space Telescope, which helped Brian Schmidt and colleagues do their &lt;a href="https://theconversation.com/nobel-prize-win-tells-us-the-universe-is-accelerating-what-does-that-mean-3753">Nobel-prize winning work&lt;/a> in 1998 to prove &lt;a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1086/300499/meta">the universe's expansion is accelerating&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With the Reddit posts, we analysed all the links to other sites and online services — more than one billion in total — to understand the dynamics of link growth, dominance and diversity through the decade.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We used a measure of link &amp;ldquo;uniqueness&amp;rdquo;. On this scale, 1 represents maximum diversity (all links have their own domain) and 0 is minimum diversity (all links are on one domain, such as &amp;ldquo;youtube.com&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A decade ago, there was a much greater variety of domains within links posted by users of Reddit, with more than 20 different domains for every 100 random links users posted. Now there are only about five different domains for every 100 links posted.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="fig1.png" alt="Our Reddit analysis showed the pool of top-performing sources online is shrinking.">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In fact, between 60-70% of all attention on key social media platforms is focused towards just ten popular domains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Beyond social media platforms, we also studied linkage patterns across the web, looking at almost 20 billion links over three years. These results reinforced the &amp;ldquo;rich are getting richer&amp;rdquo; online.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The authority, influence and visibility of the top 1,000 global websites (as measured by network centrality or PageRank) is growing every month, at the expense of all other sites.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="app-diversity-is-on-the-rise">App diversity is on the rise&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The web started as a source of innovation, new ideas and inspiration — a technology that opened up the playing field. It's now also becoming a medium that actually stifles competition and promotes monopolies and the dominance of a few players.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our findings resolve a long-running paradox about the nature of the web: does it help grow businesses, jobs and investment? Or does it make it harder to get ahead by letting anyone and everyone join the game? The answer, it turns out, is it does both.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While the diversity of sources is in decline, there is a countervailing force of continually increasing functionality with new services, products and applications — such as music streaming services (Spotify), file sharing programs (Dropbox) and messaging platforms (Messenger, Whatsapp and Snapchat).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="fig2.png" alt="Functional diversity grows continuously online.">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="website-infant-mortality">Website ‘infant mortality&amp;rsquo;&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Another major finding was the dramatic increase in the &amp;ldquo;infant mortality&amp;rdquo; rate of websites — with the big kids on the block guarding their turf more staunchly than ever.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We examined new domains that were continually referenced or linked-to in social media after their first appearance. We found that while almost 40% of the domains created 2006 were active five years on, only a little more than 3% of those created in 2015 remain active today.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dynamics of online competition are becoming clearer and clearer. And the loss of diversity is concerning. Unlike the natural world, there are no sanctuaries; competition is part of both nature and business.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our study has profound implications for business leaders, investors and governments everywhere. It shows the network effects of the web don't just apply to online businesses. They have permeated the entire economy and are rewriting many previously accepted rules of economics.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For example, the idea that businesses can maintain a competitive advantage based on where they are physically located is increasingly tenuous. Meanwhile, there's new opportunities for companies to set up shop from anywhere in the world and serve a global customer base that's both mainstream and niche.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="fig3.png" alt="Functional diversity grows continuously online.">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The best way to encourage diversity is to have more global online businesses focused on providing diverse services, by addressing consumers&amp;rsquo; increasingly niche needs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In Australia, we're starting to see this through homegrown companies such as &lt;a href="https://www.canva.com/">Canva&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://safetyculture.com/">SafetyCulture&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://iwonder.com/">iWonder&lt;/a>. Hopefully many more will appear in the decade ahead.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This article was first published by the authors on &lt;a href="https://theconversation.com/we-spent-six-years-scouring-billions-of-links-and-found-the-web-is-both-expanding-and-shrinking-159215">The Conversation&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>We spent six years scouring billions of links, and found the web is both expanding and shrinking</title><link>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/theme1_content/online_diversity/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/theme1_content/online_diversity/</guid><description>&lt;p>The online world is continuously expanding — always aggregating more services, more users and more activity. Last year, the number of websites registered on the &amp;ldquo;.com&amp;rdquo; domain &lt;a href="https://www.verisign.com/en_US/channel-resources/domain-registry-products/zone-file/index.xhtml">surpassed 150,000,000&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, more than a quarter of a century since its first commercial use, the growth of the online world is now slowing down in some key categories.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We conducted a multi-year research project analysing global trends in online diversity and dominance. &lt;a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0249993">Our research&lt;/a>, published in Public Library of Science, is the first to reveal some long-term trends in how businesses compete in the age of the web.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We saw a dramatic consolidation of attention towards a shrinking (but increasingly dominant) group of online organisations. So, while there is still growth in the functions, features and applications offered on the web, the number of entities providing these functions is shrinking.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="web-diversity-nosedives">Web diversity nosedives&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We analysed more than six billion user comments from the social media website Reddit dating back to 2006, as well as 11.8 billion Twitter posts from as far back as 2011. In total, our research used a massive 5.6Tb trove of data from more than a decade of global activity.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This dataset was more than four times the size of the original data from the Hubble Space Telescope, which helped Brian Schmidt and colleagues do their &lt;a href="https://theconversation.com/nobel-prize-win-tells-us-the-universe-is-accelerating-what-does-that-mean-3753">Nobel-prize winning work&lt;/a> in 1998 to prove &lt;a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1086/300499/meta">the universe's expansion is accelerating&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With the Reddit posts, we analysed all the links to other sites and online services — more than one billion in total — to understand the dynamics of link growth, dominance and diversity through the decade.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We used a measure of link &amp;ldquo;uniqueness&amp;rdquo;. On this scale, 1 represents maximum diversity (all links have their own domain) and 0 is minimum diversity (all links are on one domain, such as &amp;ldquo;youtube.com&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A decade ago, there was a much greater variety of domains within links posted by users of Reddit, with more than 20 different domains for every 100 random links users posted. Now there are only about five different domains for every 100 links posted.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="featured.png" alt="Our Reddit analysis showed the pool of top-performing sources online is shrinking.">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In fact, between 60-70% of all attention on key social media platforms is focused towards just ten popular domains.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Beyond social media platforms, we also studied linkage patterns across the web, looking at almost 20 billion links over three years. These results reinforced the &amp;ldquo;rich are getting richer&amp;rdquo; online.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The authority, influence and visibility of the top 1,000 global websites (as measured by network centrality or PageRank) is growing every month, at the expense of all other sites.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="app-diversity-is-on-the-rise">App diversity is on the rise&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The web started as a source of innovation, new ideas and inspiration — a technology that opened up the playing field. It's now also becoming a medium that actually stifles competition and promotes monopolies and the dominance of a few players.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our findings resolve a long-running paradox about the nature of the web: does it help grow businesses, jobs and investment? Or does it make it harder to get ahead by letting anyone and everyone join the game? The answer, it turns out, is it does both.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>While the diversity of sources is in decline, there is a countervailing force of continually increasing functionality with new services, products and applications — such as music streaming services (Spotify), file sharing programs (Dropbox) and messaging platforms (Messenger, Whatsapp and Snapchat).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="fig2.png" alt="Functional diversity grows continuously online.">&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="website-infant-mortality">Website ‘infant mortality&amp;rsquo;&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Another major finding was the dramatic increase in the &amp;ldquo;infant mortality&amp;rdquo; rate of websites — with the big kids on the block guarding their turf more staunchly than ever.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We examined new domains that were continually referenced or linked-to in social media after their first appearance. We found that while almost 40% of the domains created 2006 were active five years on, only a little more than 3% of those created in 2015 remain active today.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The dynamics of online competition are becoming clearer and clearer. And the loss of diversity is concerning. Unlike the natural world, there are no sanctuaries; competition is part of both nature and business.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Our study has profound implications for business leaders, investors and governments everywhere. It shows the network effects of the web don't just apply to online businesses. They have permeated the entire economy and are rewriting many previously accepted rules of economics.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For example, the idea that businesses can maintain a competitive advantage based on where they are physically located is increasingly tenuous. Meanwhile, there's new opportunities for companies to set up shop from anywhere in the world and serve a global customer base that's both mainstream and niche.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="fig3.png" alt="Functional diversity grows continuously online.">&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The best way to encourage diversity is to have more global online businesses focused on providing diverse services, by addressing consumers&amp;rsquo; increasingly niche needs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In Australia, we're starting to see this through homegrown companies such as &lt;a href="https://www.canva.com/">Canva&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://safetyculture.com/">SafetyCulture&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://iwonder.com/">iWonder&lt;/a>. Hopefully many more will appear in the decade ahead.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>This article was first published by the authors on &lt;a href="https://theconversation.com/we-spent-six-years-scouring-billions-of-links-and-found-the-web-is-both-expanding-and-shrinking-159215">The Conversation&lt;/a>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Causal Inference: A basic taster</title><link>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/theme1_content/causal_inference_taster/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.behavioral-ds.science/theme1_content/causal_inference_taster/</guid><description>
&lt;script src="index_files/header-attrs/header-attrs.js">&lt;/script>
&lt;link href="index_files/anchor-sections/anchor-sections.css" rel="stylesheet" />
&lt;script src="index_files/anchor-sections/anchor-sections.js">&lt;/script>
&lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="tufte.css" type="text/css" />
&lt;p>Most statistics students will be familiar with the phrase “correlation isn’t causation,” however, this doesn’t feature strongly in the remainder of their educations. To overcome this hurdle, the researchers’ best practice in experimental design is the randomized controlled trial. However, there are only specific experiments that we can perform. For example, to test the whether smoking causes cancer, we can’t force subjects to smoke. &lt;label for="tufte-mn-" class="margin-toggle">⊕&lt;/label>&lt;input type="checkbox" id="tufte-mn-" class="margin-toggle">&lt;span class="marginnote">In the 1950s the tobacco companies argued that there could be some confounding factor (a gene) which smokers and lung cancer patients shared.&lt;/span> In general, restricting ourselves to experimental studies to determine causation is incredibly limiting (especially for data scientists). We want to make the same causal conclusions from observational studies and those from experimental studies. We can do that by studying causal inference.&lt;/p>
&lt;div id="simpsons" class="section level2">
&lt;h2>Simpson’s Paradox&lt;/h2>
An example of the importance of understanding causal relationships is given by Simpson’s Paradox &lt;span class="citation">(&lt;a href="#ref-simpson1951interpretation" role="doc-biblioref">Simpson 1951&lt;/a>)&lt;/span>, which describes a peculiar phenomenon that can present in data sets, where a correlation between two variables is present in one direction but reverses in each stratum of the data. The paradox expressed best through an example:
&lt;label for="tufte-mn-" class="margin-toggle">⊕&lt;/label>&lt;input type="checkbox" id="tufte-mn-" class="margin-toggle">&lt;span class="marginnote">This appears to suggest that the more someone exercises, the higher their cholesterol is! This is absurd!&lt;/span>
&lt;div class="figure">&lt;span id="fig:simpsons-before">&lt;/span>
&lt;img src="./index_files/figure-html/simpsons-before-1.png" alt="The results of an experiment, where x-axis represents how much exercise an individual does in hours, and y-axis represents cholestral measurment for the same individual." width="672" />
&lt;p class="caption">
Figure 1: The results of an experiment, where x-axis represents how much exercise an individual does in hours, and y-axis represents cholestral measurment for the same individual.
&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
Figure &lt;a href="#fig:simpsons-before">1&lt;/a> shows a positive correlation in an experiment that measures individuals’ exercise per week and cholesterol. At first glance, this seems absurd, but when we partition the data by another causal variable, this seems reasonable:
&lt;div class="figure">&lt;span id="fig:simpsons-after">&lt;/span>
&lt;img src="index_files/figure-html/simpsons-after-1.png" alt="The same results as the experiment above, partioned by age" width="672" />
&lt;p class="caption">
Figure 2: The same results as the experiment above, partioned by age
&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>&lt;label for="tufte-mn-" class="margin-toggle">⊕&lt;/label>&lt;input type="checkbox" id="tufte-mn-" class="margin-toggle">&lt;span class="marginnote">(Also note, we have fabricated the data, although these relationships are quite plausible)&lt;/span>
Understanding the full causal story is essential. Without an entire causal narrative, we might recommend inappropriate interventions; for example, a doctor might prescribe less exercise to reduce cholesterol in the case above.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To deduce such causal stories, we need to apply the methodology of causal inference.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="structural-equation-models-and-causal-graphs" class="section level2">
&lt;h2>Structural Equation Models and Causal Graphs&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A structural equation model (SEM) is a set of equations representing the relationship between variables. For example, the equations which generated the data from &lt;a href="#simpsons">the Simpson’s paradox example&lt;/a>, are given as:
&lt;span class="math display">\[
\begin{align*}
age &amp;amp;= U_1 \\
exercise &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{13}*age + U_2 \\
cholesteral &amp;amp;= -4*exercise + age + U_3
\end{align*}
\]&lt;/span>
We can think of &lt;span class="math inline">\(U_1\)&lt;/span>, &lt;span class="math inline">\(U_2\)&lt;/span>, and &lt;span class="math inline">\(U_3\)&lt;/span> as specific unobserved exogenous variables of an individual, which generate their endogenous variables (something like error terms).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A causal graph is a DAG which describes the existence of relationships between variables in a model. An edge &lt;code>x -&amp;gt; y&lt;/code> represents the relationship &lt;code>x&lt;/code> directly causes &lt;code>y&lt;/code>. Consequently, causal graphs can represent SEMs:
&lt;img src="index_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-1-1.png" width="672" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Indeed this graph shows how age confounds the effect of exercise on cholesterol.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="do-calculus" class="section level2">
&lt;h2>Do-calculus&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;span class="citation">&lt;a href="#ref-pearl1995causal" role="doc-biblioref">Pearl&lt;/a> (&lt;a href="#ref-pearl1995causal" role="doc-biblioref">1995&lt;/a>)&lt;/span> outline a method to remove this confounding (and other similar scenarios) using do-calculus. Outlining the specifics of do-calculus is beyond the scope of this blog post (but for interested readers, we suggest &lt;span class="citation">(&lt;a href="#ref-pearl2016causal" role="doc-biblioref">Pearl, Glymour, and Jewell 2016&lt;/a>)&lt;/span>). In brief, do-calculus introduces the &lt;span class="math inline">\(do()\)&lt;/span> operator, which acts as an intervention and fixes a variable to a particular constant. For example, consider a similar binary situation to &lt;a href="#simpsons">the Simpson’s paradox example&lt;/a>, where &lt;em>exer&lt;/em> is a binary variable true if the individual is active, &lt;em>chol&lt;/em> is a binary variable true if the individual has high cholesterol, and &lt;em>age&lt;/em> is a binary variable true if the individual is over 60.&lt;/p>
&lt;pre class="r">&lt;code>bin_simpsons_data &amp;lt;- simpsons_data %&amp;gt;%
mutate(age = age &amp;gt; 60) %&amp;gt;% # Binarize the age, so those over 60 are True, and under 60 are False
mutate(exer = exercise&amp;gt;mean(exercise)) %&amp;gt;% # Binarize the exercise level, so those above the average are True, and under are False
mutate(chol = cholesteral&amp;gt;mean(cholesteral)) # Binarize the cholesteral level, so those above the average are True, and under are False&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>We ask the same experimental question; does exercise reduce cholesterol. A naive approach would be to compute the effect as &lt;span class="math inline">\(P(chol | exer = 1) - P(chol | exer = 0)=\)&lt;/span> 0.168, where &lt;span class="math inline">\(P(chol | exer)\)&lt;/span> is computed by filtering the data according to &lt;em>exer&lt;/em>. Taking this approach, we would erroneously observe that the effect was positive since those who exercise more are also old and more likely to have high cholesterol.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The experimental best practice approach would be to perform a randomized controlled trial (RCT). A random selection of individuals are assigned to &lt;em>do&lt;/em> a high exercise regiment and the others &lt;em>do&lt;/em> a low exercise regiment (regardless of age). The RCT implicitly removes the natural tendency of exercise to vary with age and allows researchers to observe the causal effect of exercise on cholesterol. When using data generated in such a fashion, increases/decreases in the probability of having high cholesterol caused by exercise are given by &lt;span class="math inline">\(P_{RCT}(chol | exer = 1) - P_{RCT}(chol | exer = 0)\)&lt;/span>. This metric is known as the Average Causal Effect (ACE), sometimes called the Average Treatment Effect. Note that by conditioning on &lt;span class="math inline">\(exer=x\)&lt;/span>, with data generated by an RCT, researchers are essentially limiting the data used to estimate &lt;span class="math inline">\(P_{RCT}(chol | exer = x)\)&lt;/span>, to individuals who were &lt;strong>forced&lt;/strong> to &lt;em>do&lt;/em> an exercise regiment &lt;span class="math inline">\(x\)&lt;/span>. The &lt;em>do&lt;/em> here represents forcing individuals to take an intervention value, regardless of their natural tendency, and this is captured by the &lt;span class="math inline">\(do()\)&lt;/span> operator. In this case, &lt;span class="math inline">\(P(chol | do(exer = x)) = P_{RCT}(chol | exer = x)\)&lt;/span>, since the data was generated with an RCT. However, RCTs can be prohibitively expensive (both in time and money) and might not be necessary to tease out a causal effect.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We would still like to estimate the ACE, &lt;span class="math inline">\(P(chol | do(exer = 1)) - P(chol | do(exer = 0))\)&lt;/span>, by using data that wasn’t generated from an RCT. By using the &lt;span class="math inline">\(do()\)&lt;/span> operator here, we aim to disassociate &lt;em>exer&lt;/em> from its natural tendency with &lt;em>age&lt;/em> and effectively perform a graph surgery:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="index_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-4-1.png" width="672" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;span class="citation">&lt;a href="#ref-pearl2016causal" role="doc-biblioref">Pearl, Glymour, and Jewell&lt;/a> (&lt;a href="#ref-pearl2016causal" role="doc-biblioref">2016&lt;/a>)&lt;/span> provide an adjustment formula for just this scenario:
&lt;span class="math display">\[
P(y|do(x)) = \sum_z \frac{P(X=x, Y=y, PA=z)}{P(X=x| PA=z)}
\]&lt;/span>
where &lt;span class="math inline">\(X\)&lt;/span> represents the variable we are acting on, &lt;span class="math inline">\(Y\)&lt;/span> the variable we measure results from, and &lt;span class="math inline">\(PA\)&lt;/span> the parents of &lt;span class="math inline">\(X\)&lt;/span> and &lt;span class="math inline">\(Y\)&lt;/span> or more generally any nodes that satisfy the back-door criterion (which we will introduce later). Note this allows us to derive the causal effect, as if we had generated data with an RCT, using only probabilities estimated from data not generated by an RCT.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As such we compute our ACE for the binary scenario:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre class="r">&lt;code># The Joint Distribution P(age, exer, chol) i.e. P(x,y,z)
p_aec &amp;lt;- bin_simpsons_data %&amp;gt;%
count(age, exer, chol) %&amp;gt;%
mutate(freq = n/sum(n))
# The Marginal Distribution P(age) i.e. P(z)
p_a &amp;lt;- bin_simpsons_data %&amp;gt;%
count(age) %&amp;gt;%
mutate(freq = n/sum(n))
# The Marginal Distribution P(age, exer) i.e. P(x, z)
p_ea &amp;lt;- bin_simpsons_data %&amp;gt;%
count(age, exer) %&amp;gt;%
mutate(freq = n/sum(n))
# The Conditional Mariginal Distribution P(exer | age) i.e. P(x | z)
p_e_a &amp;lt;- p_a %&amp;gt;%
right_join(p_ea, by=&amp;quot;age&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;%
mutate(freq = freq.y/freq.x) %&amp;gt;%
select(age, exer, freq)
# The Intervention Distribution P(chol | do(exer)) i.e. P(y | do(x))
probabilities &amp;lt;- data.table(p_aec %&amp;gt;%
left_join(p_e_a, by=c(&amp;quot;age&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;exer&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;%
mutate(freq = freq.x/freq.y) %&amp;gt;%
select(age, exer, chol, freq) %&amp;gt;%
filter(chol) # We are only concerned with what cause high cholestral
)
# The average causal effect of exer on chol
ACE &amp;lt;- sum(probabilities[exer==T, freq]) - sum(probabilities[exer==F, freq]) &lt;/code>&lt;/pre>
&lt;p>This procedure leads to a negative ACE of -0.175, which shows the causal effect of going from high to low exercise on the probability of getting high cholesterol.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A natural question that follows from this example is, under what conditions can we use such adjustments to achieve an identifiable causal effect.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="d-seperation" class="section level2">
&lt;h2>d-seperation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>To understand common scenarios where the effect of variable &lt;span class="math inline">\(X\)&lt;/span> on &lt;span class="math inline">\(Y\)&lt;/span> is identifiable within a causal graph, we must first introduce the concept of d-separation, also known as blocking. A pair of variable &lt;span class="math inline">\(X\)&lt;/span> and &lt;span class="math inline">\(Y\)&lt;/span> are said to be blocked if they are conditionally independent, given a set of nodes &lt;span class="math inline">\(Z\)&lt;/span>. There are three graph types, which are essential for blocking:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="index_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-7-1.png" width="672" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the chain scenario, &lt;span class="math inline">\(X \sim Y\)&lt;/span> is blocked by conditioning on &lt;span class="math inline">\(Z={M}\)&lt;/span>. This is sometimes refered to as the mediation scenario, which we will address further in &lt;a href="#front-door">the front-door criterion&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="index_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-8-1.png" width="672" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the fork scenario, &lt;span class="math inline">\(X \sim Y\)&lt;/span> is blocked by conditioning on &lt;span class="math inline">\(Z={Z}\)&lt;/span>. This is sometimes refered to as the confounder scenario, which is the situation in &lt;a href="#simpsons">the simpson’s paradox example&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="index_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-9-1.png" width="672" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Finally, in the collider scenario, &lt;span class="math inline">\(X \sim Y\)&lt;/span> is blocked by &lt;em>not&lt;/em> conditioning on &lt;span class="math inline">\(Z={M}\)&lt;/span>. The idea that &lt;span class="math inline">\(X\)&lt;/span> and &lt;span class="math inline">\(Y\)&lt;/span>, which are independent, to begin with, can become conditionally dependant is unintuitive. One way to think about this is that we are sharing information received from $ Y $ with $ X $ through $ M $ when we condition on $ M $. For a more thorough investigation into this phenomenon, refer to &lt;span class="citation">(&lt;a href="#ref-pearl2016causal" role="doc-biblioref">Pearl, Glymour, and Jewell 2016&lt;/a>)&lt;/span>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A path is said to be blocked by &lt;span class="math inline">\(Z\)&lt;/span> if it contains a chain or fork with its middle node in &lt;span class="math inline">\(Z\)&lt;/span> or a collider with its middle node not in &lt;span class="math inline">\(Z\)&lt;/span>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We are now ready to introduce the main criteria for which we can perform adjustments.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="the-backdoor" class="section level2">
&lt;h2>The Backdoor&lt;/h2>
&lt;div class="definition">
&lt;span id="def:unnamed-chunk-10" class="definition">&lt;strong>Definition 1 (The Backdoor Criterion) &lt;/strong>&lt;/span>A set of nodes &lt;span class="math inline">\(Z\)&lt;/span>, given a DAG &lt;span class="math inline">\(G\)&lt;/span> and a pair of nodes &lt;span class="math inline">\((X,Y)\)&lt;/span>, is said to satisfy the backdoor criterion if no node in &lt;span class="math inline">\(Z\)&lt;/span> is a descendant of &lt;span class="math inline">\(X\)&lt;/span>, and &lt;span class="math inline">\(Z\)&lt;/span> blocks all paths between &lt;span class="math inline">\(X\)&lt;/span> and &lt;span class="math inline">\(Y\)&lt;/span>, which contain arrows into &lt;span class="math inline">\(X\)&lt;/span>.
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>If there exists are set of nodes why satisfy the backdoor criterion, then the effect of &lt;span class="math inline">\(X\)&lt;/span> on &lt;span class="math inline">\(Y\)&lt;/span> is identifiable and given by:
&lt;span class="math display">\[
P(y|do(x)) = \sum_z \frac{P(X=x, Y=y, Z=z)}{P(X=x| Z=z)}
\]&lt;/span>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The backdoor criterion stops undue influence through the &lt;em>backdoor&lt;/em> paths; it leaves direct paths between &lt;span class="math inline">\(X\)&lt;/span> and &lt;span class="math inline">\(Y\)&lt;/span>, and it blocks spurious paths.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It is clear that { &lt;em>age&lt;/em> } satisfies these conditions to be a backdoor adjustment set in the example above.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="index_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-11-1.png" width="672" />&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="front-door" class="section level2">
&lt;h2>The Front-door&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>There are notably common scenarios where this doesn’t work. For example, consider a constructed causal mediation situation, as follows:
&lt;img src="index_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-12-1.png" width="672" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this case we cannot use the backdoor criterion, to detect the effect of &lt;em>smoking&lt;/em> on &lt;em>cancer&lt;/em> because &lt;em>tar&lt;/em> is a descendant of &lt;em>smoking&lt;/em>, and there exists no direct link between &lt;em>smoking&lt;/em> and &lt;em>cancer&lt;/em>. We must use instead the frontdoor criterion:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="definition">
&lt;span id="def:unnamed-chunk-13" class="definition">&lt;strong>Definition 2 (The Frontdoor Criterion) &lt;/strong>&lt;/span>A set of nodes &lt;span class="math inline">\(Z\)&lt;/span>, given a DAG &lt;span class="math inline">\(G\)&lt;/span> and a pair of nodes &lt;span class="math inline">\((X,Y)\)&lt;/span>, is said to satisfy the frontdoor criterion if; &lt;span class="math inline">\(Z\)&lt;/span> intercepts all direct paths from &lt;span class="math inline">\(X\)&lt;/span> to &lt;span class="math inline">\(Y\)&lt;/span>, all paths between &lt;span class="math inline">\(X\)&lt;/span> and &lt;span class="math inline">\(Z\)&lt;/span> are blocked, and all backdoor paths between &lt;span class="math inline">\(Y\)&lt;/span> and &lt;span class="math inline">\(Z\)&lt;/span> are blocked by &lt;span class="math inline">\(X\)&lt;/span>.
&lt;/div>
&lt;p>If there exists are set of nodes &lt;span class="math inline">\(Z\)&lt;/span> which satisfy the frontdoor criterion, and &lt;span class="math inline">\(P(x, z)&amp;gt;0\)&lt;/span>, then the effect of &lt;span class="math inline">\(X\)&lt;/span> on &lt;span class="math inline">\(Y\)&lt;/span> is identifiable and given by:
&lt;span class="math display">\[
P(y|do(x)) = \sum_z P(z|x) \sum_{x^\prime} P(y|x^\prime, z)P(x^\prime)
\]&lt;/span>
In our smoking scenario, we see that by adjusting for &lt;em>tar&lt;/em> , we can observe the effect of &lt;em>smoking&lt;/em> on &lt;em>cancer&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="conclusion" class="section level2">
&lt;h2>Conclusion&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The above briefly outlines a core motivation for studying causal inference and causal stories. We summarise some of the underlying theory of causal inference and show practical methodology through the &lt;em>frontdoor&lt;/em> and &lt;em>backdoor&lt;/em> criterion for determining causal effects through entirely observational studies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are notable aspects of causal inference we have omitted from this taster. The most gaping is the lack of an explanation for the powerful tool of counterfactuals. We have only presented binary examples here (aside from our motivating example); however, perhaps the most common and useful causal inference application is to continuous examples using regression with linear models. Ultimately, we decided this was beyond causal inference taster’s scope and were more deserving of their own articles. Again, for the interested reader, we recommend &lt;span class="citation">&lt;a href="#ref-pearl2016causal" role="doc-biblioref">Pearl, Glymour, and Jewell&lt;/a> (&lt;a href="#ref-pearl2016causal" role="doc-biblioref">2016&lt;/a>)&lt;/span>, which adds links to many other resources.&lt;/p>
&lt;div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
&lt;div id="ref-pearl1995causal" class="csl-entry">
Pearl, Judea. 1995. &lt;span>“Causal Diagrams for Empirical Research.”&lt;/span> &lt;em>Biometrika&lt;/em> 82 (4): 669–88.
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="ref-pearl2016causal" class="csl-entry">
Pearl, Judea, Madelyn Glymour, and Nicholas P Jewell. 2016. &lt;em>Causal Inference in Statistics: A Primer&lt;/em>. John Wiley &amp;amp; Sons.
&lt;/div>
&lt;div id="ref-simpson1951interpretation" class="csl-entry">
Simpson, Edward H. 1951. &lt;span>“The Interpretation of Interaction in Contingency Tables.”&lt;/span> &lt;em>Journal of the Royal Statistical Society: Series B (Methodological)&lt;/em> 13 (2): 238–41.
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>